
1. Effects of BT-11 treatment on hippocampal gene expression in Male Fisher transgenic 344-AD rats. [Male RNAseq]
(Submitter supplied) 5 month old Male Fisher transgenic 344-AD (Tg-AD) rats expressing human Swedish amyloid precursor protein (APPsw) and Δ exon 9 presenelin-1 (PS1ΔE9) were treated with BT-11  (cat. no. HY-102013, MCE) at 8.5 mg/kg body weight administered in rodent chow. Following 6 months of BT-11  treatment, rats (11 months of age) were tested for cognitive behaviour prior to sacrificing. Hippocampal Brain region were dissected and  RNA sequencing (RNAseq) analyses was done on the Isolated sample. more...
Organism:	Rattus norvegicus
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL23945 10 Samples
FTP download: GEO (XLS) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE280nnn/GSE280024/
Series		Accession: GSE280024	ID: 200280024

1. Effects of BT-11 treatment on hippocampal gene expression in Female Fisher transgenic 344-AD rats. [Female RNAseq]
(Submitter supplied) 5 month old Female Fisher transgenic 344-AD (Tg-AD) rats expressing human Swedish amyloid precursor protein (APPsw) and Δ exon 9 presenelin-1 (PS1ΔE9) were treated with BT-11  (cat. no. HY-102013, MCE) at 8.5 mg/kg body weight administered in rodent chow. Following 6 months of BT-11  treatment, rats (11 months of age) were tested for cognitive behavior prior to sacrificing. Hippocampal Brain region were dissected and  RNA sequencing (RNAseq) analyses was done on the Isolated sample. more...
Organism:	Rattus norvegicus
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL25947 10 Samples
FTP download: GEO (XLSX) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE280nnn/GSE280023/
Series		Accession: GSE280023	ID: 200280023

1. Identification of pathological pathways centered on circRNA dysregulation associated with irreversible progression of Alzheimer’s disease [circGigyf2KD]
(Submitter supplied) Background Circular RNAs (circRNAs) are highly stable regulatory molecules, often accumulated in the mammalian brain and thought to serve as “memory molecules” that govern the long process of aging. Mounting evidence demonstrated circRNA dysregulation in postmortem cortical regions of Alzheimer’s disease (AD) patients. However, whether and how circRNA dysregulation underlies AD progression remains unexplored. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL34290 6 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TXT) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE272nnn/GSE272745/
Series		Accession: GSE272745	ID: 200272745

1. Identification of pathological pathways centered on circRNA dysregulation associated with irreversible progression of Alzheimer’s disease [5xFADHippocampus]
(Submitter supplied) Background Circular RNAs (circRNAs) are highly stable regulatory molecules, often accumulated in the mammalian brain and thought to serve as “memory molecules” that govern the long process of aging. Mounting evidence demonstrated circRNA dysregulation in postmortem cortical regions of Alzheimer’s disease (AD) patients. However, whether and how circRNA dysregulation underlies AD progression remains unexplored. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus
Type:		Non-coding RNA profiling by high throughput sequencing; Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL34290 12 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TXT, XLS) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE272nnn/GSE272744/
Series		Accession: GSE272744	ID: 200272744

1. Antenatal Glucocorticoid Exposure Induced Neurodegenerative Changes in the Fetal Ovine Hippocampal Transcriptome Independent of Pulmonary Immaturity
(Submitter supplied) [Background] Antenatal steroid (ACS) therapy conveys lifesaving benefits to the preterm fetus. However, current treatments are associated with increased risk of growth, endocrine, and neurodevelopmental abnormalities. [Objectives] To inform ACS therapy optimisation we used a sheep model of pregnancy to test whether adverse fetal brain effects were independent of respiratory benefit and ACS pharmacokinetics. more...
Organism:	Ovis aries
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL27721 48 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TSV) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE248nnn/GSE248786/
Series		Accession: GSE248786	ID: 200248786

1. Alzheimer’s disease-linked risk alleles elevate microglial cGAS-associated senescence and neurodegeneration in a tauopathy model [bulk_RNAseq]
(Submitter supplied) The strongest risk factors for Alzheimer’s disease (AD) include the 4 allele of apolipoprotein E (APOE), the R47H variant of triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells 2 (TREM2), and female sex. Here, we combine APOE4 and TREM2R47H (R47H) in female P301S tauopathy mice to identify the pathways activated when AD risk is the strongest, thereby highlighting disease-causing mechanisms. We find that the R47H variant induces neurodegeneration in female APOE4 mice without impacting hippocampal tau load. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL24247 24 Samples
FTP download: GEO (CSV) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE254nnn/GSE254103/
Series		Accession: GSE254103	ID: 200254103

1. Endogenous p53 Inhibitor TIRR Dissociates Systemic Metabolic Health from Oncogenic Activity - RNAseq data
(Submitter supplied) It is unclear whether metabolic health corresponds to reduced oncogenesis or vice versa. We study Tudor-interacting repair regulator (TIRR), an inhibitor of p53 binding protein 1 (53BP1)-mediated p53 activation, and the physiological consequences of enhancing tumor suppressor activity. Deleting TIRR selectively activates p53, significantly protecting against cancer but leading to a systemic metabolic imbalance in mice. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL23479 82 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TSV, TXT) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE210nnn/GSE210900/
Series		Accession: GSE210900	ID: 200210900

1. Integrative multi-omics analysis reveals conserved cell-projection deficits in human Down syndrome brains [TotalRNAseq]
(Submitter supplied) Down syndrome (DS) is the most common genetic cause of cognitive disability. However, it is largely unclear how the triplication of a small gene subset may impinge on diverse aspects of DS brain physio-pathology. Here, we took a multi-omics approach and simultaneously analyze by RNA-seq and proteomics the expression signature of two diverse regions of human postmortem DS brains. We found that the overexpression of triplicated genes triggered global expression dysregulations differentially affecting transcripts, miRNA and proteins involved in both known and novel candidate pathways. more...
Organism:	Homo sapiens
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL24676 42 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TXT) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE221nnn/GSE221178/
Series		Accession: GSE221178	ID: 200221178

1. Integrative multi-omics analysis reveals conserved cell-projection deficits in human Down syndrome brains [smallRNAseq]
(Submitter supplied) Down syndrome (DS) is the most common genetic cause of cognitive disability. However, it is largely unclear how the triplication of a small gene subset may impinge on diverse aspects of DS brain physio-pathology. Here, we took a multi-omics approach and simultaneously analyze by RNA-seq and proteomics the expression signature of two diverse regions of human postmortem DS brains. We found that the overexpression of triplicated genes triggered global expression dysregulations differentially affecting transcripts, miRNA and proteins involved in both known and novel candidate pathways. more...
Organism:	Homo sapiens
Type:		Non-coding RNA profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL24676 42 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TXT) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE221nnn/GSE221130/
Series		Accession: GSE221130	ID: 200221130

1. Cross-species analysis uncovers the mitochondrial stress response in the hippocampus as a shared mechanism in mouse early life stress and human depression
(Submitter supplied) Depression, or major depressive disorder, poses a significant burden for both individuals and society, affecting approximately 10.8% of the general population. This psychiatric disorder leads to approximately 800,000 deaths per year. A combination of genetic and environmental factors such as early life stress (ELS) increase the risk for development of depression in humans, and a clear role for the hippocampus in the pathophysiology of depression has been shown. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL24247 21 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TXT) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE254nnn/GSE254134/
Series		Accession: GSE254134	ID: 200254134

1. Functional Interaction between APOE4 and mutant APP promotes cerebrovascular changes in young animals
(Submitter supplied) The Apolipoprotein E4 (ApoE4) allele is one of the strongest risk factors for late-onset Alzheimer’s disease (AD) and is associated with a breakdown of the blood-brain barrier and vascular dysfunction (Nation et al 2019; Liu and Bu 2022). Importantly, these vascular pathologies are exacerbated when APOE4 is coexpressed with familial mutations in APP or components of the γ-secretase complex (Montagne and Zlokovic 2021), suggesting that the interactions between APOE4 and AD mutations can drive progression of the disease. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL24247 15 Samples
FTP download: GEO (CSV) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE242nnn/GSE242751/
Series		Accession: GSE242751	ID: 200242751

1. Neuroprotective potential of intranasally delivered L-myc immortalized human neural stem cells in female rats after a controlled cortical impact injury
(Submitter supplied) Efficacious stem cell-based therapies for traumatic brain injury (TBI) depend on successful delivery, migration, and engraftment of stem cells to induce neuroprotection. L-myc expressing human neural stem cells (LMNSC008) demonstrate an inherent tropism to injury sites after intranasal (IN) administration. We hypothesize that IN delivered LMNSC008 cells migrate to primary and secondary injury sites and modulate biomarkers associated with neuroprotection and tissue regeneration. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus; Rattus norvegicus
Type:		Expression profiling by array
Platform: GPL25652 20 Samples
FTP download: GEO (RCC, XLSX) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE242nnn/GSE242031/
Series		Accession: GSE242031	ID: 200242031

1. IMPDH2 filaments protect from neurodegeneration in AMPD2 deficiency
(Submitter supplied) Metabolic dysregulation is one of the most common causes of pediatric neurodegenerative disorders. However, how the disruption of ubiquitous and essential metabolic pathways predominantly affect neural tissue remains unclear. Here we use a mouse model of AMPD2 deficiency to study cellular and molecular mechanisms that lead to selective neuronal vulnerability to purine metabolism imbalance. We show that AMPD deficiency in mice primarily leads to hippocampal dentate gyrus degeneration despite causing a generalized reduction of brain GTP levels. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL24247 18 Samples
FTP download: GEO (BW) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE253nnn/GSE253045/
Series		Accession: GSE253045	ID: 200253045

1. SPLICER: A Highly Efficient Base Editing Toolbox That Enables in vivo Exon Skipping For Targeting Alzheimer’s Disease
(Submitter supplied) This SuperSeries is composed of the SubSeries listed below.
Organism:	Mus musculus; Homo sapiens
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing; Other
Platforms: GPL15520 GPL16417 GPL24676 183 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TAB, TXT, XLSX) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE246nnn/GSE246588/
Series		Accession: GSE246588	ID: 200246588

1. Bulk RNAseq of post-mortem brain tissue of Aicardi-Goutières Syndrome patients and non-diseased controls
(Submitter supplied) Post mortem brain tissue of three Patients suffering from Aicardi-Goutières Syndrome from different brain regions was used to isolate RNA and perform RNAseq analysis compared to age matched control patients with no underlying brain pathology.
Organism:	Homo sapiens
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL15433 18 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TSV) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE162nnn/GSE162414/
SRA Run Selector: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/study/?acc=PRJNA681821
Series		Accession: GSE162414	ID: 200162414

1. FMRP deficiency leads to multifactorial dysregulation of splicing and mislocalization of MBNL1 to the cytoplasm
(Submitter supplied) Fragile X syndrome (FXS) is a neurodevelopmental disorder that is often modeled in Fmr1 knockout mice where the RNA-binding protein FMRP is absent. Here, we show that in Fmr1-deficient mice, RNA mis-splicing occurs in several brain regions and peripheral tissues. To assess molecular mechanisms of splicing mis-regulation, we employed N2A cells depleted of Fmr1. In the absence of FMRP, RNA-specific exon skipping events are linked to the splicing factors hnRNPF, PTBP1, and MBNL1. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platforms: GPL24247 GPL19057 56 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TSV, TXT) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE207nnn/GSE207145/
Series		Accession: GSE207145	ID: 200207145

1. Embryonic stem cell-derived neurons as a model system for epigenome maturation during development
(Submitter supplied) DNA methylation in neurons is directly linked to neuronal genome regulation and maturation. Unlike other tissues, vertebrate neurons accumulate high levels of atypical DNA methylation in the CH sequence context (mCH) during early postnatal brain development. Here we investigate to what extent neurons derived in vitro from both mouse and human pluripotent stem cells recapitulate in vivo DNA methylation patterns. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus
Type:		Methylation profiling by high throughput sequencing; Third-party reanalysis; Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platforms: GPL18480 GPL16417 GPL24247 53 Samples
FTP download: GEO (BIGWIG, GTF, TXT) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE137nnn/GSE137098/
SRA Run Selector: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Traces/study/?acc=PRJNA564548
Series		Accession: GSE137098	ID: 200137098

1. A TDP-43 acetylation-mimic mutation that disrupts RNA-binding drives FTLD-like neurodegeneration in a mouse model of sporadic TDP-43 proteinopathy
(Submitter supplied) TDP-43 proteinopathies including frontotemporal lobar dementia (FTLD) and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) are devastating neurodegenerative disorders characterized by aggregation and mislocalization of the nucleic-acid binding protein TDP-43 and subsequent neuronal dysfunction. Here, we developed an endogenous model of sporadic TDP-43 proteinopathy based on the principle that disease-associated TDP-43 acetylation at lysine 145 (K145) alters TDP-43 conformation, impairs its RNA-binding capacity, and induces downstream mis-regulation of target genes. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL24247 20 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TXT) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE216nnn/GSE216294/
Series		Accession: GSE216294	ID: 200216294

1. Multi-modal characterization and simulation of human epileptic circuitry
(Submitter supplied) Temporal lobe epilepsy is the fourth most common neurological disorder with about 40% of patients not responding to pharmacological treatment. Increased cellular loss in the hippocampus is linked to disease severity and pathological phenotypes such as heightened seizure propensity. While the hippocampus is the target of therapeutic interventions such as temporal lobe resection, the impact of the disease at the cellular level remains unclear in humans. more...
Organism:	Homo sapiens
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL11154 4 Samples
FTP download: GEO (CSV, MTX, TSV) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE216nnn/GSE216877/
Series		Accession: GSE216877	ID: 200216877

1. The epigenetic reader PHF21B modulates social memory and synaptic plasticity-related genes in mice
(Submitter supplied) Plant homeodomain (PHD) finger proteins are epigenetic readers whose dysfunctions are implicated in neurological conditions, but the molecular mechanisms linking PHD protein deficits to disease remain unclear. Here we generated a PHD finger protein 21B (Phf21b)-depleted mutant CRISPR mouse model (Phf21bΔ4/Δ4) to examine its roles in the brain. KO animals exhibited impaired social memory. Reduced expression of synaptic proteins and impaired long-term potentiation were observed in the KO hippocampi. more...
Organism:	Mus musculus
Type:		Expression profiling by high throughput sequencing
Platform: GPL19057 6 Samples
FTP download: GEO (TXT) ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/series/GSE201nnn/GSE201477/
Series		Accession: GSE201477	ID: 200201477
